<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act for leavying of some forces for securing the peace of the kingdom untill the meeting of the Parliament</title>
            <author>Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16239599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16239599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58561)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1600:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act for leavying of some forces for securing the peace of the kingdom untill the meeting of the Parliament</title>
                  <author>Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105143:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ACT FOR LEAVYING OF SOME FORCES For Securing the PEACE OF THE KINGDOM, Untill the meeting of the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105143:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105143:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Edinburgh, 14.</hi> October, <hi>1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Act for Leavying ſome Forces, for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Peace of the Kingdom untill the meeting of the Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Committee of Eſtates, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how neceſſary it is that ſome Forces bee raiſed for ſecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peace of the Country, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Forces of theſe who were in Arms in and about <hi>Stirling,</hi> and of their adherents who by Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Warrants, or encouragement from them, have taken Arms to the endangering of the Peace of the Kingdom; And untill theſe who are now in Arms in the <hi>Iſleſ, Highlands</hi> and Northern Shires of this Kingdom, for whoſe disbanding their was no undertaking by the Articles of agreement, be fully disbanded, and put out of a condition of troubling the Kingdom, and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Peace thereof; Taking alſo into their conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration the many Inſolencies and diſorders commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thoſe that are disbanded, and that diverſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality, and others that were in the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Service, have not ſignified their agreement and ſubmiſſion to the ſaid Articles of Treaty, but are rather indeavouring by Inteſtine Inſurrection, or Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Invaſion, to overthrow the grounds of that late
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105143:3"/>agreement, and in purſuance of their own ends to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the troubles of the Kingdom; And the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> having deſired this Kingdom to uſe all means to prevent and ſuppreſſe any deſign of reinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a new Engagement againſt that Kingdom, to the weakning of the Amity and Union between both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; And the Committee of Eſtates, in diſcharge of the truſt committed to them, being moſt deſirous and carefull to preſerve the Peace of the Kingdom, untill the next enſuing Parliament, to which the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all queſtions and differences relating to the publick good are referred; Have therefore thought it neceſſary and expedient, and do hereby Ordain, that the number of two Thouſand ſeven Hundred and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Foot, and the number of ſix Hundred and twenty Horſe, be forthwith Levied and kept on foot, as a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding force in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there are above ſeven Hundred Foot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready together, That the particular numbers of Horſe and Foot underwritten, be preſently raiſed in the Shires following, <hi>viz.</hi> Out of the Sherifdoms of <hi>Rox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> and <hi>Selkirk</hi> Fourſcore and twelve Foot, and one and twenty Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Berwick</hi> Fourſcore and twelve Foot, and one and twenty Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Haddingtoun,</hi> Foureſcore and twelve Foot, and one and twenty Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Fourſcore and twelve Foot, and one and twenty Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Lithgow</hi> fourty Foot, and twelve Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Peebles,</hi> twenty nine Foot, and ſeven Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Dumfreis,</hi> Fourſcore and twelve Foot, and twenty five Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Wigtoun</hi> and <hi>Kilkudbright,</hi> Fourſcore and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105143:3"/>twelve Foot, and twenty four Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Renfrew,</hi> Fourſcore and twelve Foot, and fourty two Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Lanerk,</hi> one Hundred and ſix Foot, and one and fourty Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Sterling</hi> and <hi>Clackmanan,</hi> Fourſcore and one Foot, and twenty five Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Fyff</hi> and <hi>Kinroſhire,</hi> one Hundred and eighteen Foot, and fourty eight Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Pearth,</hi> one Hundred and ſeventy Foot, and fourty eight Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Forfar,</hi> one Hundred and ſixteen Foot, and twenty nine Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kairdin</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Marſhals</hi> part of <hi>Aberdeinſhire,</hi> Fourſcore and twelve Foot, and eleven Horſe. Out of the reſt of the Sherifdom of <hi>Aberdein,</hi> and out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Bamff,</hi> one Hundred twenty and three Foot, and fifty ſeven Horſe. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Elgin, Narine,</hi> and that part of <hi>Innerneſſe</hi> one this ſide of <hi>Neſſe,</hi> one Hundred and eighteen Foot, and twenty five Horſe. Out of the Earl of <hi>Seaforth</hi> and Lord <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatts</hi> diviſion of <hi>Innerneſſe,</hi> Fourſcore and one Foot, and twenty five Horſe. Out of the Earl of <hi>Seaforthes</hi> part of <hi>Innerneſſe, Sutherland</hi> and <hi>Cathnes,</hi> one hundred twenty &amp; three Foot, and twenty five Horſe. Out of the Marqueis of <hi>Argyles</hi> diviſion of <hi>Innerneſſe</hi> and <hi>Badze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noche,</hi> fourſcore and four Foot. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Bute</hi> ſix Foot. Out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Dunbartan</hi> three Horſe. The Sherifdom of <hi>Argyle</hi> exeemed, be reaſon of the late vaſtation thereof. Out of the Sherif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Orkney,</hi> fourſcore and four Foot.</p>
            <p>And to the end that the Forces abovewritten may be the better Ordered, Regulated and diſpoſed of, to the beſt advantage for the preſent Service of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105143:4"/>The Committee of Eſtates Ordains the whole number of Foot to be divided into ſix Regiments, and commanded in manner following, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Laird of <hi>Lawer's</hi> be continued Colonel of a Regiment conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of ſix hundred and fifty men effectively<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And to the end that the ſaid number may be made up and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, he is to have out of <hi>Pearth-Shire</hi> one hundred men. And out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Peebles</hi> 29. That Generall Major <hi>Holburne</hi> have the command as Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of a Regiment of Foot, conſiſting of four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, whereof he is to have out of <hi>Roxburgh</hi> and <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk Shire</hi> 92. Out of <hi>Berwick Shire</hi> 92. Out of <hi>Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingtoun Shire,</hi> 92. Out of <hi>Lanerk Shire,</hi> 106. Out of <hi>Lithgow Shire</hi> 18. Inde four hundred. And ordains the ſaid General Major <hi>Holburne</hi> to be Governour of the Caſtle of <hi>Stirling,</hi> and to place therein the number of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> men, out of his foreſaid Regiment. That Lievtenant Colonell <hi>James Meinzies</hi> have the command of a Regiment, conſiſting of five hundred Foot, <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Orknies</hi> 84. Out of <hi>Pearth-Shire</hi> 59. Out of <hi>Forfar</hi> 32. Out or Kinkairdin and <hi>Marſhalls</hi> part of <hi>Aberdein,</hi> 92. Out of the reſt of <hi>Aberdein</hi> and <hi>Bamff Shire,</hi> 128. Out of <hi>Elgin, Nairne,</hi> and that part of <hi>Innerneſſe</hi> on this ſide of the Water of <hi>Neſſe,</hi> 100. Foot. Out of which Regiment, the foreſaid Colonel is to Gariſon <hi>Ennerlochy, Dowart,</hi> and the Ruthven of <hi>Badzenoch.</hi> That Sir <hi>James Friſſell</hi> have the command as Colonel of a Regiment of Foot, conſiſting of three hundred, which are to be placed for a Garriſon in the Town of <hi>Innerneſſe, viz.</hi> That he have out of <hi>Elgin, Nairne,</hi> and that part of <hi>Innerneſse,</hi> on this ſide of the Water of <hi>Neſſe,</hi> 18. Out of <hi>Seafort,</hi> and <hi>Lovats</hi> diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Innerneſſe</hi> 82. Out of <hi>Seaforth</hi> part of <hi>Innerneſſe, Sutherland,</hi> and <hi>Cathnes,</hi> 123. Out of <hi>Argyles</hi> part of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105143:4"/>
               <hi>Innerneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Badzenoch,</hi> 84. That Colonel
<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pitſcotty</hi> have the command of a Regiment of Foot, conſiſting of four hundred; <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Stirling,</hi> and <hi>Clackmanan-Shires,</hi> 71. Out of <hi>Fyffe,</hi> and <hi>Kinro-Shires,</hi> 118. Out of <hi>Pearth-Shire,</hi> 11. Which with hoſe under his command already on Foot, makes 400. Out of which number, he is to place a ſufficient Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Town of S. <hi>Johnſtoune,</hi> and in the Houſes of the <hi>Blair</hi> of <hi>Atholle,</hi> and <hi>Garth.</hi> That Colonel <hi>John Innes</hi> have the command as Colonel of a Regiment of Foot, conſiſting of four hundred, <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Lithgow,</hi> 22. Out of <hi>Edinburgh-Shire,</hi> 92. Out of <hi>Dumfreis-Shire,</hi> 92. Out of <hi>Wigtoun,</hi> and <hi>Kilcudbright,</hi> 91. Out of <hi>Air,</hi> and <hi>Renfrew,</hi> 92. And out of <hi>Stirling-Shire,</hi> 10. Out of which number, he is to place ane ſufficient Garriſon, in the Houſes of <hi>Strabogie,</hi> and <hi>Boge</hi> of <hi>Gight.</hi> And Ordains out of the Sherifdom of <hi>Forfar,</hi> fourty men to be placed, as a Garriſon for the Caſtle of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and other fourty men for the Caſtels of <hi>Dumbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and <hi>Duglas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the better regulating of the foreſaid num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Horſe, the Committee of Eſtates, nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats, appoints and Ordains the Lord <hi>Chancellour</hi> to have the command of ane Troop, conſiſting of 80. Horſemen; which proportion, is voluntarily and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered to be advanced to his Lordſhip by the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> And that the <hi>Lord Generall</hi> his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,</hi> ſhall have the command of ane Troop of Horſe conſiſting, of 60. <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Roxburgh,</hi> and <hi>Selkirk-Shires,</hi> 41. And out of <hi>Berwick</hi> 19. That Lievtenant Generall <hi>David Leſly</hi> have the command of a Troop, conſiſting of 60, <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Lanerk</hi> 12. And out of <hi>Fyffe</hi> 48. That Colonel <hi>Robert Mongomry,</hi> have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105143:5"/>the command of a Troop conſiſting of 60. <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Dumfreis</hi> 25. Out of <hi>Galloway</hi> and <hi>Kirkcudbright</hi> 4. And out of <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Renfrew</hi> 11. That Colonel <hi>Scot,</hi> have the command of a Troop as Ruitmaſter thereof, conſiſting of 60. <hi>viz.</hi> Out of that part of <hi>Aberdein</hi> not belonging to the Earl of <hi>Marſhals</hi> part of the <hi>Shire,</hi> 46. One of <hi>Elgin, Nairne,</hi> and that part of <hi>Innerneſse</hi> on this ſide of the Water of <hi>Neſſe.</hi> 14. That Colonell <hi>Gilbert Ker</hi> have the command of a Troop, as Ruitma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thereof, conſiſting of 60, <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Elgin, Nairn,</hi> and that part of <hi>Innerneſſe,</hi> one this ſide of the Water of <hi>Neſſe</hi> 11. Out of the Lord <hi>Seafort</hi> and Lord <hi>Lovats</hi> diviſion of <hi>Innerneſſe</hi> 25. Out of <hi>Seaforths</hi> part of <hi>Innerneſſe, Sutherland</hi> and <hi>Caithnes</hi> 25. Out of <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bartan</hi> 5. <hi>Inde</hi> 66. And becauſe of the great diſtance of the places allocat to the ſaid <hi>Gilbert Ker,</hi> and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of raiſing his ſaid proportion out of the ſame, the Generall Commiſſar is hereby Ordained to give him allowance in money for ſuch men as cannot be well raiſed out of thoſe parts, to make up his Troop of the ſaid number of 60, as is appointed. That Major <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chane</hi> have the command of a Troop as Ruitmaſter thereof, conſiſting of 60, <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Berwick-Shire</hi> 2. Out of <hi>Haddingtoun Shire</hi> 21. Out of <hi>Edinburgh-Shire</hi> 21. Out of <hi>Lithgow-Shire</hi> 12. Out of <hi>Stirling Shire</hi> 4. Inde 60. That Major <hi>William Stewart</hi> have the command of a Troop as Rutmaſter thereof, conſiſting of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Stirling-Shire</hi> 9. Out of <hi>Forfar</hi> 29. Out of <hi>Kinkardin,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Marſhals</hi> part of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> 11. Out of <hi>Bamff Shire</hi> 11. inde 60. That
<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Robert <hi>Hacquet</hi> be Ruitmaſter of a Troop, conſiſting of 60. <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Pearth</hi> 48. Out of <hi>Stirling</hi> 12. inde 60. That L. Col <hi>James Lundy</hi> be Ruitmaſter of a Troop conſiſting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105143:5"/>of 60. <hi>viz.</hi> Out of <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Renfrew</hi> 31. Out of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerk</hi> 29. <hi>Inde</hi> 60.</p>
            <p>And to the end the countrey may not be further bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with Billettings and Quarterings of Souldiers, after the ſaid Forces ſhall once be raiſed and delivered to their ſeverall Commanders, at the dayes of Rande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouze after mentioned; the Committee of Eſtates Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, the haill Officers, Troops and Regiments afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to have locall aſſignments given to them by the Generall Commiſſary upon the ſeverall Shires, for their maintenance and entertainment; And that it may appear that the eſtabliſhment of the ſaid maintenance is made proportionably, and with as great eaſe to the Countrey as poſſibly may be. The Committee doth Ordain and allow that the ten Ruitmaſters above ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſhall each of them have of pay monethly, two hundred pound Scots, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 2000. l. Ten Lievtenants of Horſe, each of them an hundred pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 1000. l. Ten Cornets, each of them an hundred marks monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 0666. l. 13. ſh. 4. d. Ten Quartermaſters of Troops, at fourty five pound a piece, monethly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Inde</hi> 450. l. Thirty Corporalls at 36 pound a piece month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Inde</hi> 1080. l. Ten Trumpets, each of them thirty ſix pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem</hi> 360. l. Ten Farriors or Smiths, each of them thirty pound monethly, <hi>Inde</hi> 300. l. Six hundred and twenty common Troopers, each of them 16. ſh. a day <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 14880.</p>
            <p>And true every one of the foreſaid ſix Colonels of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105143:6"/>the Foot Regiments, ſhall have each of them two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound of monethly pay, <hi>Inde per menſem</hi> 1200. l. Majors of Foot, each of them an hundred pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 600. l. Twenty ſix Captains of Foot, each of them an hundred marks monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 1733. l. 6. ſh. 8. d. Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſix Lievtenants of Foot, each of them fourty pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 1040. l. Twenty ſix En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, each of them thirty pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 786. Six Regiment Quartermaſters, each of them fourty pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 240. l. Six Proveſt-Marſhalls, each of them fourty pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 240. l. Fifty and two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jants, each of them eighteen pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 936. l. Seventy eight Corporals, each of them twelve pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 936. l. Fifty two Drumers or Pypers, each of them twelve pound monethly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 624. Twenty ſix Captains at Arms, each of them fifteen pound moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Inde per menſem.</hi> 390. Two thouſand ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty common Souldiers each of them 6. ſh. <hi>per diem. Inde per menſem</hi> 25389.</p>
            <p>And to the effect the ſeverall Shires and Burghs in the Kingdom be not unneceſſarily burthened and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by falſe muſters, and ſo pay for men who are not in Service, the Committee of Eſtates Nominats and Ordains <hi>Hugh Kennede</hi> to be Generall Muſtermaſter, and allows to him two hundred pound <hi>per menſem,</hi> for his ſervice, commanding him monethly or quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take a ſurvey of each Regiment, Troop and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105143:6"/>Company of the foreſaid Forces, and to take up a liſt of the true number thereof, and this to be done in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a Generall Officer, where the ſame can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently had; With power to him to put in due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution all former Acts made againſt falſe Muſters.</p>
            <p>And further, the ſaid Committee diſcharges all free quarterings of officers or ſouldiers after the day of Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devous underwritten apointed for the foreſaid forces, &amp; prohibits any to be quartered in Noblemen or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes, without ſpeciall order from the Comittee of Eſtates, or ſome Generall Officer for that effect. And that this may be the better put to execution, the Committee nominats and appoints the Laird of <hi>Arnot</hi> younger of that ilk to be General quartermaſter, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him two hundred pounds monethly for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and commanding him to take ſpecial care that the Kingdom be not further burthened with free quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, but that he be carefull to ſee all former Acts of Parliament to be put into due execution, which have been made to reſtrain the abuſes anent quarterings.</p>
            <p>And to the end the ſeveral ſummes of money to bee paid throughout the whole Shires and Burghs of this Kingdom, for maintenance and entertainment of the forſaid forces appointed to be kept up for the publick good may be the better collected, and for ſupplying of the publick neceſſities of the Kingdom in time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and for diſcharging the publick debts which have been contracted ſince the firſt of <hi>September</hi> laſt, for arms, amunition, proviſions and other neceſſaries for the forces which were lately on foot under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105143:7"/>of his Excellency the Earl of <hi>Leaven,</hi> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates nominates and appoints Sir <hi>James Stewart</hi> Provoſt of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Generall Collector, With power to him to ſubſtitute deputs in ilk Shire, and to appoint a Clerk of collection, Which collector deputs, as well of Shires as of Burghs and Pariſhes, and Clerk of collection ſhall have ſuch like fees as is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Act of Taxt and Loan, and that to be uplifted out of the ſaid Shires and Pariſhes, by and at-over the ſaid maintenance; and the Burghs to be free, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they collect their Taxt upon their own charges; With power alſo to the ſaid General Collector, to put all the former Acts of Parliament ſtanding yet unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, to due execution, ſo far as may conduce to the better and eaſier ingathering of the maintenance.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Committee of Eſtates likewiſe allowes to his Excellencie the Lord General, one Secretary, and to have <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> monethly for his attendance, and the like to the Lievtenant General to have <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> monethly for his attendance.</p>
            <p>It is further Ordained, that each Governour of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Towns, or houſes within this Kingdom, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the number of fifty men or above in garriſon, ſhall have an hundred Merks monthly, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under that number to have the pay of a Lieutenant of Foot: And allows to his Excellency, preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the Caſtell of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> one Lieutenant, one Sarjant, two corporalls two Gunners, one Smith, one Wright and one Drummer. And ordains, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the 16. of <hi>October</hi> inſtant 1648. their be only four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105143:7"/>Souldiers entertained in the ſaid Caſtle, and that the allowance of ſuch of them as the exchequer should maintaine, be repeted from the Exchequer.</p>
            <p>Moreover it is hereby ſpecially provided and Odain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Committees of War, (conſiſting onely of ſuch perſons as have not been acceſſory to the late En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt <hi>England</hi>) in the ſeverall Shires, and particularly in the Sheriffdoms of <hi>Clidſdail, Air, Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frew, Galloway</hi> and <hi>Kirkcudbright, Teviodail, Midlothian, Lithgow, Dumbartan</hi> and <hi>Fiffe</hi> take ſpeciall care to levie the foreſaid proportions of Horſe and Foot appointed to be put forth by each Shire upon the charges of thoſe alane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, who are diſ affected, and have been promoters of the late unlawfull Engagement againſt <hi>England:</hi> And that thoſe onely who came forth in arms againſt the authors and abettors of the late Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and continued with the Army untill they were diſmiſſed by order, and ſuch other perſons who have declared themſelves againſt the Engagement, oppoſed the Enemy at home, and are known to have been conſtantly wel-affected to this Cauſe, &amp; particularly ſuch Noblemen, Gentlemen or Burgeſſes who diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Parliament, be exempted and made free from all charges and expences in this Levie.</p>
            <p>And the Committee of Eſtates having ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the manifold dangers and inconveniences from time to time iſſuing and ariſing to the ſtraight, vigorous and active proſecution of the Cauſe and Covenant of God within this Kingdom, through the want of that due care and circumſpectnes that ought to be uſed in the choice of Officers and Souldiers worthy to be imployed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105143:8"/>in ſo good a Cauſe, as the ſad experience of former and late times hath made too evident: Have therefore Ordained, and by theſe preſents appoints and Ordains, that all the Shires and Burghs within this Kingdom faithfully endeavour to ſend forth in this Levie the ableſt and beſt affected men they can have, and none but ſuch as are of good life and converſation, teſtified under the hand of the Miniſter of the Pariſh or Seſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof where they live; And that they carefully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the ſending forth of any Souldiers that have been in Armes for the late Engagement; And if they ſhall be neceſſitated to employ any of them, that upon no pretence any other be admitted, but ſuch as ſhall have teſtimonials of their Repentance for joyning in the late Engagement from the Miniſter of their Pariſh, or other ways from the Commiſſion of the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; and ſhall give their faithfull promiſe never to plead or ſpeak in time coming publickly nor privately in defence or in favour of the late moſt unlawfull En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt <hi>England;</hi> And the Generall Muſter-Maſter is hereby ſpecially Ordained to receive Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificats from all ſuch Troopers and Foot Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that are or deſires to be imployed in this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and have been in the late Engagement, of their Repentance, and ſatisfaction given according to the Articles concluded by the Commiſsion of the late Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly of the Kirk, under the hands of the Miniſters or Seſſions of the Garriſons where they live or from the Commiſsion of the General Aſſembly; And whoſoever produce not ſuch certificats, ſhal not be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105143:8"/>admitted to this ſervice, and the out-reikers of ſuch ſhall be forced to put out others in their place; and the Commanders and Superior Officers are hereby Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to uſe their faithfull endeavours that thoſe Souldiers which are to be Levied and put under their command, be qualified as is before expreſſed, with certification, that if they ſail, their ſhall be no allowance of Levie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money granted to them that ſhall preſent the ſaid Souldiers.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there be in this Kingdom a competent number of very faithfull, able and honeſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Officers, who by the ſpeciall providence of God and his ſingular mercy to this diſtreſſed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, have all this time kept themſelves free, and have not been involved in the guiltineſſe of the late unlawful Engagement, nor have ſuffered themſelves to be infna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or entangled by the alluring baits of outward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and profits; ſo that it were both againſt the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of policy as well as piety, to intruſt thoſe with the charge of commanding our Forces or any part thereof, who have been lately in Armes againſt us: Therefore the Committee of Eſtates Ordains, that no Officers who have been employed, or acceſſory to the late unlawful Engagement againſt <hi>England,</hi> ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon any terms to bear charge in this new modell, and that the Committee may have the more full aſſurance of the punctual performance hereof; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains all the Ruitmaſters and Colonels of Foot foreſaid to give in perfect Liſts of all the inferiour Officers to be imployed by them, to be approven or not approven
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105143:9"/>by the ſaid Committee; with certification that the Committee will proceed to appoint inferior Officers to all ſuch as within <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> houres after notice hereof, ſhall not give in there foreſaid liſts.</p>
            <p>And the Committee doth hereby declare, that it ſhall be left to the option and arbitriment of ſuch Commanders and Officers as are of known integrity, and qualified as is before expreſſed, to take from the ſeverall Shires and Burghs, either the number and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of men and Horſes that are to be put forth by the ſaid Shires and Burghs, Or to take the ſume of eightſcore pounds for each Horſeman and the ſume of fourty pounds for ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Footman, providing alwayes, that if any of the ſaid Commanders ſhall chooſe rather to take money, then Horſe or men from the Shires; in that caſe they are to furniſh and provide men able, welaffected, and qualified as is before expreſſed, as they will be anſwerable to the Committee of Eſtates, With certification that if they having received moneys for Horſe and men, doe notwithſtanding faill, in raiſing and preſenting Horſe and men to the Generall Muſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter at the time of Randezvous, or that the men rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and preſented by them, ſhall want certificats of their qualification in manner before expreſſed, not onely ſhall the Souldiers wanting ſuch certificats be rejected, and not admitted upon the ſervice, but alſo the leavy-moneys of thoſe Souldiers are not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the Officers, but to be refounded if they have received any, and the Officers themſelves to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered with diſgrace.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105143:9"/>
            <p>And for the more ſpeedy raiſing of the foreſaid num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and proportion of Horſe and Foot: The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates Ordains all Heretors, Proper Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetters, Life Renters and other Subject in out-putting of Horſe and Foot conform to the Acts of Parliament, (excepting always ſuch as are before declared to be eximed by this Act) To put out their proportion of Horſe and Foot well armed, and well mounted, the Foot two part with Muskets, and third part pikes, and all with ſwords: And to bring their ſeverall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Horſe and Foot armed and provided as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to the pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Rendezvous in each Shire, to be delivered to their ſeverall Officers under the pain of four hundred Merks for each deficient Horſeman, and under the pain of a hundred pound for each deficient Footman not brought to the foreſaid Rendezvous, which are hereby ordained to be kept at the Dyets following, <hi>viz.</hi> all the Shires on the South ſide of <hi>Tay</hi> upon the twenty ſixt day of this moneth, and thoſe upon the North ſide thereof upon the third day of <hi>November</hi> or at furtheſt within ſix dayes, after inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation hereof, ſhall be given to the ſeverall Shires by the foreſaid Officers, or to the Committees of War therein as they are now conſtituted by Warrants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord Chancellour his hand: And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee Ordains the ſaid Colonells of Foot and Rute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters to be aſſiſting to the Committees of War in the ſeveral Shires (ſecluding from the ſaid Committees ſuch as are before excluded) in poynding and diſtrenzing the goods of any heretors &amp; others foreſaid who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in outputting either of the Horſe or Foot at leaſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105143:10"/>in giving money therefore: <hi>viz.</hi> for every Horſman wanting at the day of Randezvous the ſome of 400. marks from every heretor and others foreſaid who are lyable to put them out, and for every Footman wanting, the ſumme of 100. pounds, and further declares that the foreſaids deficients ſhall be eſteemed as Enemies to and hinderers of the publick ſervice of this Kingdom and the good of this cauſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mr. <hi>Tho. Henderſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105143:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
